Guide to the Ukrainian National Association Branch No. 63 Records, 1907-1966 AIS.1979.29
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ukrainian National Association Branch No. 63 (Ford City, Pa.) Records
1907-1966
1925-1955
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Ukrainian National Association. Branch 63 (Ford City, Pa.)
AIS.1979.29
1.86 Linear Feet (6 boxes; 1 microfilm reel)
This collection includes the records of Branch No. 63 of the Ukrainian National Association from 1907-1966. This particular branch was founded in 1903 in Ford City, Pa., in order to help Ukrainian immigrants in the region adjust to their new home, while at the same time preserving their social and cultural heritage. The records include meeting minute books, account books, membership materials, Ukrainian publications and branch documents, and insurance policy books.
Previous Citation
Ukrainian National Association Branch No. 63 (Ford City, Pa.) Records, 1907-1966, AIS.1979.29, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Separated Material
The volumes in the Insurance Policy Books section were microfilmed and originally given the accession number AIS.1979.37. It is available in the Archives Service Center reading room microfilm cabinet.
Scope and Content Notes
The records of the Ukrainian National Association Branch No. 63 document the existence of the organization in Ford City, Pennsylvania, from 1907-1966, with the bulk of the material from the years 1925-1955. The collection contains a variety of material including branch event information; a limited amount of correspondence; several publications in Ukrainian, including one issue of the UNA's newspaper, Svoboda; branch tax receipts and licenses; meeting minute books; account books; and a variety of membership material, including applications and cards. It is important to note that most of the material is written in Ukrainian. In the meeting notes, sometimes an English translation follows the Ukrainian entry. The meeting minute books provide information on Branch No. 63's monthly or bi-monthly meetings of the trustees and officers, with discussions on recurring themes such as financial matters, membership, and activities taking place at and maintenance of the Ukrainian National Association Home in Ford City. Many of the ledgers include loose-leaf material, such as correspondence and liquor license renewals. The account books show monthly membership dues and branch and UNA Home income and expenses. There are only membership applications and cards from 1953-1966, while account and minute books stop in 1955.
History
The Ukrainian National Association (UNA) was founded in 1894 and is the oldest and most progressive Ukrainian fraternal order, with branches in the United States and Canada. The organization sought to help the first wave of immigrants from Ukraine to adjust to their new surroundings, while at the same time celebrating and preserving their social and cultural heritage through music, dance, cuisine, language and religious customs.
Branch No. 63 of the Ukrainian National Association was founded in 1903 in Ford City, Pennsylvania. Original members consisted of a small group of eighteen Ukrainian immigrants who settled in the region. Michael Beck served as the first president of the branch, with Sam Ball as the secretary. In 1909, Branch No. 187 was formed, but merged with Branch No. 63 on July 26, 1914.
Charter members first met at St. Joseph's Hall on Fourth Avenue in Ford City. After the flood of 1913, members loaned the organization enough funds to purchase a building at 600 Sixth Avenue from the Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company for $3000. The building had formally housed the community's first public school and was turned into the Ukrainian National Home. In 1916, Branch No. 63 purchased some adjoining land in Ford City. The organization's work, meetings, and social activities, such as weddings, concerts and dances, took place at the home.
By 1952, the year the branch celebrated its Golden Jubilee, membership reached 528 men, women and children; the UNA Branch No. 63 was reportedly the largest branch in Pennsylvania. In the fall of 1957, a new building was constructed for the Ukrainian National Home and a dedication ceremony held in February 1958.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Correspondence; Ledgers (Account books); Minutes (Administrative records); Societies; Ethnic groups; Bylaws (Administrative records); Fraternal organizations -- Pennsylvania; Ukrainians -- Pennsylvania; Ukrainian Americans -- Pennsylvania; Ukrainians -- Pennsylvania -- Ford City; Ukrainian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Ford City; Ukrainian Americans -- Pennsylvania -- Ford City -- Societies and clubs; Ukraine -- Emigration and immigration; Pennsylvania -- Emigration and immigration; Ukrainians -- Pennsylvania -- Emigration and immigration; Ukrainian National Association. Branch 63 (Ford City, Pa.)
- Anniversary Celebrations and Dedication Ceremonies, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- By-Laws, 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- By-Laws, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Certificate, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1942-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Publications (Ukrainian), 1918, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
- Svoboda, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Tax Receipts and Licenses, 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Account Books, 1907-1955
  - Financial Ledger, 1907-1911 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Financial Ledger, 1923-1937 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Financial Ledger, 1926-1942 (Box 2, Volume 3)
  - Financial Ledger, 1927-1937 (Box 2, Volume 4)
  - Financial Ledger, 1929-1931 (Box 2, Volume 5)
  - Financial Ledger, 1937-1949 (Box 2, Volume 6)
  - Financial Ledger, 1940-1951 (Box 3, Volume 7)
  - Financial Ledger, 1942-1949 (Box 3, Volume 8)
  - Financial Ledger, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Volume 9)
  - Financial Ledger, 1952-1955 (Box 4, Volume 10)
- Meeting Minutes, 1927-1955
  - Meetings Ledger, 1927-1936 (Box 4, Volume 11)
  - Meetings Ledger, 1936-1943 (Box 4, Volume 12)
  - Meetings Ledger, 1936-1944 (Box 5, Volume 13)
  - Meetings Ledger, 1945-1949 (Box 5, Volume 14)
  - Meetings Ledger, 1945-1950 (Box 5, Volume 15)
  - Meetings Ledger, 1955 (Box 5, Volume 16)
- Membership Material, 1946-1966
  - Membership Applications, 1953-1966, undated (Box 6, Item 1)
  - Membership Cards, 1959-1966 (Box 6, Item 2)
  - Membership Dues Book, 1946-1953 (Box 6, Item 3)
  - Membership Applications, Ukrainian National Home, Inc., January 1956 (Box 6, Item 4)
- Insurance Policy Books, 1902-1953
  Scope and Content Notes
  The volumes in the Insurance Policy Books section are available on microfilm under the collection number AIS.1979.37.
  - Volume 1, 1902-1907 (Microfilm-cabinet 2, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - Volume 2, 1908-1913
  - Volume 3, 1913-1928
  - Volume 4, 1927-1942
  - Volume 5, 1942-1953